Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is ו vav
עמוד א amud aleph and we're in the middle of a pretty
interesting challenging סוגיא sugya about having sex for the first time on
שבת. Shabbos. Before we go any further I want to just point
out a comment that I made a week ago when we were
or a little over a week ago even just five days ago
four days ago when we started the דף daf of כתובות Kesuvos
which was that this is called like a mini ש״ס. Shas. And
I want to just bring your attention to how many different topics
we have managed to touch on in the last four pages. Okay
so we started with the issue about when the בתולה besulah gets
married and then dealt with the question about when a marriage is
delayed like whether you have to when whether the groom has to
pay for support. That's all within the theme of the מסכת. maseches.
But then very quickly on עמוד ב amud beis we got to
the issue about conditions by a גט get and when not being
able to fulfill the condition would still be considered to be like
you fulfilled it so a whole major question about contracts and stipulations
and גיטין. gittin. And then on ג gimmel we got to the
whole issue about הפקעת קידושין hafka'as kiddushin when the Rabbis would retroactively
dissolve a marriage. And then we turned to back to the major
theme about when you would get married but then quickly on ג
עמוד ב gimmel amud beis we dealt with the whole issue about
a case of where there's somebody has to submit to having sex
with the ruler of the town or else be willing to give
up their life getting to issues about יהרג ואל יעבור yaharog v'al
ya'avor right? And then we turned to the whole issue about אבילות
aveilus אנינות aninus questions about when the I'm sorry about if the
parents die right before the wedding are you allowed to postpone you
know put you know sort of postpone the funeral in order to
get married? So that was all these interesting אבילות aveilus and אנינות
aninus questions right? And when would you know what would sort of
be practiced and the דברים שבצנעה נוהג devarim she'betzina noheg etc.
And then also so we've got now what do we have? We
have אבילות aveilus אנינות aninus יהרג ואל יעבור yaharog v'al ya'avor גיטין.
gittin.
And then we've got and then we have the whole issue about
נדה niddah and when there's a
חופת נדה chuppas niddah and sleeping in separate rooms.
And then we went
to again the and then from that we turned on on דף
ה daf hey to the question about what types of things you're
allowed to talk about on שבת Shabbos and doing חשבונות cheshbonos on
שבת. Shabbos. And then finally back to some major issues about כתובות
Kesuvos which is about the date and about ברכה beracha and why
you get married on a certain day because of the ברכה שנאמרה
בו לאדם beracha she'ne'emra bo l'adam and ברכה שנאמרה בו לדגים beracha
she'ne'emra bo l'dagim etc. And then a little אגדתא agadata about not
listening to לשון הרע lashon hara and why our ears are the
way they are. And then finally anyway back to this issue right
about having sex for the first time on שבת Shabbos and all
these technical שבת Shabbos questions
about making a wound and making a פתח pesach and אינו מתכוין
aino miskaven and מקלקל. miskalkel. So if you think about it that's
a lot to cover in four דף daf just in terms of
I mean any review of four דף daf I might mention a
lot of topics but in terms of the range of themes in
which we've addressed here נדה niddah אבילות aveilus גיטין gittin שבת Shabbos
right? All of that within just like you know four דף. daf.
So I think you have an appreciation why this is called like
a ש״ס קטן Shas Katan and why this is learned a lot
in ישיבות yeshivos just because of the range of issues and also
because the סוגיות sugyot tend to get to like the heart of
an issue right? It's not like a long drawn out סוגיא sugya
which works around the periphery for many days. Like all of these
סוגיות sugyot really sort of got to like the heart of these
central conceptual questions. That being said you know the issue here should
be mentioned about having sex for the first time on שבת Shabbat
and the question that gets raised about whether is this wounding or
not wounding? Is it like that the actual you know skin is
breaking? Is the blood being released from like behind a barrier or
is the blood really being released because of a type of you
know it's being torn from the wall and therefore it releases blood
from within like the wall vessels? And then the question about what
is the groom's intent? Does the groom want to see the blood
to know that his bride is a virgin? Does he want to
make the opening in order to make his bride who is a
virgin into a non-virgin so that now they'll be beginning a sexual
life together so that's considered to be like something desirous right? That
now as husband and wife she won't be a virgin anymore or
is that somehow seen as you know ruining her pristine state? So
all of these things it should be mentioned when you learn this
מסכת masechet in the ישיבה yeshiva are taught to like you know
teenage boys. And what really you know I think should point out
that I think what is bothersome about that is not the fact
that you're sort of talking about you know body parts to teenage
boys I think that we should have a healthy conversation about those
things but I think the problem is is that you know all
of this
discussion the whole question about you know again like wanting to to
make her a non-virgin, wanting to see the blood, but what is
this act that this man is doing to this woman and how
does it look like from the perspective of the man? And you
know and I think that there's you know raises really challenges of
how of whether to keep this to boys of a certain age
and how to teach it and how to you know raise these
types of issues, which I don't think that they ever do get
raised when this is taught. So I just you know really wanted
to point that out because it's a it's like a difficult גמרא
Gemara to learn, not I think because it's explicit but because of
the way it sort of you know maybe these other questions that
have to be raised and one could say so the גמרא Gemara
always objectifies things in order to to submit it to a halakhic
analysis, but nevertheless you know this does I think create challenges in
this particular context of being sort of looked at from the man's
perspective and you know and the way to talk about making an
opening in the woman, releasing the blood, releasing the blood for the
purpose of knowing she's a בתולה, betulah, you know and all of
those things focused on the man doing this act and what his
intent is and the woman sort of being seen as somewhat of
a object in this process. Anyway, those are the issues that come
up in the גמרא Gemara with two different sort of approaches. I
won't go through the whole decision chart that the גמרא Gemara made,
but basically to basically distill it, you know the here are two
possible prohibitions, here are two possible ways that this is a problem:
either that it is a חבורה chaburah depending on if that's how
the גמרא Gemara understood the physiology or it and that's one possibility,
and it definitely also is a פתח. petach. And then the question
is and that presumably is an איסור issur of בנין, binyan, which
is an interesting idea of a concept of בנין binyan applying to
people although we have that in some other גמרות. gemarot. And then
the idea of that so those are the two possible prohibitions we
have and then the question is is it מתכוון mitkaven or does
the person have intent for this or not have intent for this,
is he מכוון mechaven or אינו מכוון, eino mechaven, does it matter
if he has intent and is it an issue of מקלקל mekalkel
and maybe there's a special הלכה halacha by חבורות chaburot that since
wounding is always somewhat of a destructive act that maybe even if
you're מקלקל mekalkel you're חייב. chayav. So those are the various types
of factors to consider here. I should mention two points about this
about you know about this. Number one the question of what type
of a מלאכה melacha is creating a חבורה. chabura. So תוספות Tosafot
makes a you know shows pretty clearly that it's categorized under the
category of נטילת נשמה netilat neshamah like the same way you can't
שחט shecht an animal, so making a חבורה chabura is like a
mini שחטing, shecht but the question is mini-taking of life, how is
it a mini-taking of life? And you could conceptualize that in two
ways. So one way תוספות Tosafot says is that you is that
it weakens the person to some degree. So a wounding
is halfway to or a quarter of the way or a hundredth
of the way to kill him. Or the other thing is not
because it somehow hurts the person or the living thing but because
the very extraction of blood represent blood represents life. And תוספות Tosafot
says that it has to be the latter because if it were
the former why would this גמרא Gemara be considering it like it's
an intentional מלאכה melacha that you might be doing it, there's no
desire to wound the woman to cause her pain to cause her
weakness or whatever. The only way the גמרא Gemara sort of says
it's considered to be that you're מכוון mechaven and that you're doing
it for its own purpose is that because the man wants to
see the blood to know that the woman is a בתולה. betulah.
So that really defines the idea of נטילת נשמה netilat neshamah almost
symbolically because the blood represents life regardless of whether it's hurting the
person or not hurting the person. So that's in terms of defining
what the prohibition is in terms of making a wound. And the
other thing to point out, very important conceptual point is that the
גמרא Gemara says well maybe wants to know that if the making
of the wound maybe you're still חייב chayav because maybe a position
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that מקלקל בחבורה חייב mekalkel bechabura chayav
that even when you make a
wound even if it's a destructive act by making a wound you're
still going to be חייב. chayav. Okay so that's a special idea
as I said because wounding often is destructive so maybe that's an
exception to the rule and even when it's destructive you're חייב. chayav.
So תוספות Tosafot asks the question, תוספות Tosafot says one minute if
you're חייב chayav when you're מקלקל mekalkel that means that we waive
the normal demands criteria for מלאכת מחשבת melechet machshevet that שבת Shabbat
you're only חייב chayav when it's considered to be like a
constructive strictly intentional act. If that's true then why does the גמרא
Gemara think that you need to have כוונה kavanah according to רבי
שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Why does the גמרא Gemara say that אינו מכוון
eino mechaven you'd be פטור pattur for רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? If
for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you're חייב chayav for מקלקל mekalkel you
should also be חייב chayav for אינו מתכוון. eino mitkaven. And תוספות
Tosafot makes an important point and he says אינו מתכוון eino mitkaven
is not a distinctive שבת Shabbat requirement or מכוון mechaven I should
say is a requirement by all prohibitions and therefore what רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is saying is that by מקלקל mekalkel or we're going
to waive the special שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* criteria and say you're חייב
chayav, *chayav* even though it's destructive because that's to be constructive is
a special שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* criteria. But the idea that you're exempt
when you don't have כוונה *kavanah* for is to is a generic
requirement is not a שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* requirement. So again, if you're
in the middle of learning הלכות שבת hilkhos Shabbos *Hilchos Shabbos*, that's
an important distinction like I said because כתובות Ketubot *Kesubos* is like
a ש"ס קטן *Shas Katan* where we are in the middle of
learning הלכות halachos. שבת Shabbos, *Hilchos Shabbos* right now, and we're going
to spend a lot of the remainder of today in terms of
הלכות שבת Shabbos. *Hilchos Shabbos*, so it is an important conceptual point
that even though מקלקל mekalkel בחבורה *mekalkel be-chaburah*, by the way, it
comes up because, you know, somebody sometimes let's say somebody needs a
to have an injection on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, so and that might
draw blood right and like, you know, can you do certain things?
How do you deal with אינו מתכוון eino miskaven *aino miskavein*? If
מקלקל mekalkel בחבורה *mekalkel be-chaburah* is חייב chayav *chayav* in שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbos*, is אינו מתכוון eino miskaven *aino miskavein* also אסור assur. *assur*?
And תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* makes the point that no, אינו מתכוון eino
miskaven *aino miskavein* as emerges from this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is a
different issue. Right, גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if it's אינו מתכוון eino
miskaven *aino miskavein* you're פטור patur. *patur* even according to רבי שמעון
Rabi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* even though it's a חבורה *chaburah* because that's
a general idea by מלאכות *melachos* by prohibitions not for שבת Shabbos
*Shabbos*. If you want to see it in תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, top
of ו עמוד א *vav amud aleph*, he says like this.
דטעם שניהם דפטורין בשאר מלאכות שבת Shabbos *detam sheneihem depeturin beshaar melachos
Shabbos*—he's talking about מקלקל mekalkel *mekalkel* and מתעסק *misasek*—הוי משום דבעינן מלאכת
מחשבת *havei mishum debe'inan meleches machsheves*.
So that's why those things might not apply by חבורה *chaburah*. אבל
avel שאינו מתכוון כלל למלאכה *aval she-aino miskavein klal le-melachah*, but if
you're not trying to do it at all, you're trying to do
something completely different, לא משום דבעינן מלאכת מחשבת מיפטר *lo mishum debe'inan
meleches machsheves mister*, that's not a unique שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* idea of
מלאכת מחשבת *meleches machsheves*, דבשאר מקומות נמי פטר אינו מתכוון eino miskaven
*deshaar mekomos nami piter aino miskavein*. It's an exemption by other prohibitions,
כגון גבי כלאים *kegon gabei kilayim*, דמוכרי כסות מוכרין כדרכן ובלבד שלא
יתכוונו *demochei kesus mochin kedarko ubilvad she-lo yiskaveinu*, ותני נמי נזיר חופף
ומפספס *vetannai nami nazir chofif umefatpetz*, a נזיר *nazir* can comb his
hair even though it might pull out some strands. הלכך בחבורה נמי
שרי *hilkach be-chaburah nami shari*. Therefore it remains an exemption by a
wound even if מקלקל mekalkel *mekalkel* does not. So I want to
make that point, very interesting conceptual point not just about חבורה *chaburah*
but about sort of what types of שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* criteria are
uniquely to שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* and which ones are general. Yes, Michael,
you had a question.
Mean, you know, you think conceptually about whether it's מלאכה melakha *melacha*
or לשמה *lishma* and part of the distinction would be let's say
cause bruising without blood, cause a black and blue mark, right?
Right, yeah, right, except then the question is maybe the blood came
out of its vessels and just got trapped under the skin. גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is actually clear that you would be חייב chayav *chayav*
by a black and blue mark because it breaks the vessels underneath
the skin.
One other question. I mean you may have covered this right before
I came in. If this all from the man's perspective, does it
mean that from a woman that even though it could be תיקון
tikun *tikkun* she'd be okay because she's being, if you will, like
the one is being done to? Right.
That's exactly what I was saying. This is all the man doing
the act and sort of seeing the woman here completely not, nobody's
asking if the woman's allowed to have sex on שבת Shabbos?
*Shabbos*. Right now, which I mean, assuming that we just don't know,
right?
Right, and it's seen as also sort of being framed as irrelevant.
You know, obviously maybe we do know, but it's irrelevant, right. That's
why I say that this is all very much the man's perspective
and it's like it's objectifying the woman's body and making her sort
of somewhat irrelevant to the fact.
We can't tell you anything about whether she'd be okay for her.
We can't.
Correct. Right. Yeah.
The negative aspect of the blood of a wound also has a
positive aspect in this context because it's going to lead to life.
You mean because eventually, because it means that it's the starting a
sexual life and whatever. Yeah, that's right, right. So that would be
but yeah, but that's exactly it that there could be an aspect
of תיקון *tikkun* here by the חבורה *chaburah*. Okay, so fine, so
now let's now actually actually start reading the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And
I assume that דב *Dov* mentioned yesterday, or if not I'll mention
that, you know, how could the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* here be saying
אינו מתכוון eino miskaven, *aino miskavein*, you know, isn't it a case
of a פסיק רישא psik reisha, *psik reisha*? Isn't it something that's
definitely going to happen? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*
both ask the question and we're going to get to it today
where the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to say how sometimes it
could happen and without the hymen breaking and it won't be a
פסיק רישא psik reisha. *psik reisha*, but shh, we'll talk about it,
but what should be noted though is that the idea that it
makes a difference if it's a פסיק רישא psik reisha. *psik reisha*,
if it'll definitely happen, is not explicit in the debate of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי Rebbe מאיר *Rabbi Meir*—I mean
רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*. That gets introduced by אביי
Abaye ורבא *Abaye and Rava*. Now it is true that the whole
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* yesterday was the סתם *stam*, so the סתם *stam*
knew of אביי Abbaye ורבא *Abaye and Rava*. The סתם *stam* is
obviously later. But nevertheless, just because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't mention
פסיק רישא psik reisha *psik reisha*, it's interesting whether the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* at that stage, you know, how much we assume that that's
always has to be part of the conversation. You also realize, right,
it is interesting the way that entire discussion, like an almost entire
עמוד *amud* with, you know, sort of creating a whole decision chart,
if you say like this and like this and like this, it
sort of conceptually frames the possibilities. It's all sort of the סתם
*stam*. There's no, you know, so it's there and you know we'll
see later a סוגיא sugya. *sugya* that might seem like the original
סוגיא Sugya. *sugya* of our גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. and
you know sort of introduction. So let's take a look now where
we continue. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בבי רב Bebei
Rav start on the first line, I think maybe you did this
at the end of yesterday, but so what, we'll start. This is
a good lead in. Okay. בבי רב אמרי, Bebei Rav amri, in
the house of רב, Rav, in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב Rav
they say, רב שרי ושמואל אסור. Rav shari veShmuel assur. רב Rav
says it's permissible to have sex for the first time on שבת,
Shabbos and שמואל Shmuel says it's forbidden. בנהרדעא, Binhar-da'a, in נהרדעא, Neharde'a,
which was שמואל's Shmuel's city and him where his ישיבה Yeshiva was,
אמרי רב אסור ושמואל שרי. amri Rav assur veShmuel shari. The opposite.
רב Rav says it's forbidden and שמואל Shmuel says it's permissible. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק סימנך, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak simancha, the
way to remember it is, אלו מקלין לעצמן ואלו מקלין לעצמן. eilu
mikilin le-atzman ve-eilu mikilin le-atzman. Each ישיבה Yeshiva says that their רבי
פוסקנס paskens it's מותר. muttar. Okay, and therefore so they're being מיקל
meikel for themselves that whatever happened for them, they would be allowed
to have sex for the first time on שבת. Shabbos? Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, ורב שרי? veRav shari? Does רב Rav
really say that it is permissible? והאמר רב שימי בר חזקיה משמיה
דרב האי מסוכרייא דניזייתא Veha-amar Rav Shimi bar Chizkiya mishmeih deRav hai
mesukhraya dinayata
which is basically a rag
that
is stuck into the hole of the side of a barrel of
wine. Okay, so אסור להדוקה ביומא טבא. assur lehadoka beyoma tova.
You can't tighten it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, presumably not on
שבת Shabbos also, for whatever reason it's being said by יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Okay, now what's the assumption of what the problem would
be? So there's a huge תוספות Tosafos here. So the problem רש"י
Rashi says is, if you squeeze, you tighten it and it wrings
out some of the wine, and it's סחיטה. sekhita. Now the problem
תוספות Tosafos asks is, so the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is
a proof that רב Rav פוסקנס paskens אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is
אסור. assur, And without going through all of the different decision charts
that the גמרא Gemara made yesterday, it's clear that if אינו מתכוין
eino mitkavein is אסור, assur, it's much more likely that it would
be forbidden to have sex on שבת, Shabbos right? Because a lot
of things are, different things are happening, but are you really intending
them or not? But if אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein is אסור, assur.
it's going to be a problem. So the basic upshot the גמרא
Gemara wants to say is you see that רב Rav says אינו
מתכוין eino mitkavein is אסור. assur But the question that תוספות Tosafos
asks is like if it's about squeezing, what's the איסור issur of
squeezing? So if the איסור issur of squeezing is cleaning, if like
laundering, so that, and that does seem to be the case by
גמרא, Gemara because that's what you do when you launder, you soak
clothes in water and then you wring them out. So תוספות Tosafos
says well then all the evidence points to the idea that it
only applies by water. It wouldn't apply by other liquids. I mean,
okay, you want to get the wine out because it's staining, but
it's not the same type of thing where the wringing of the
liquid is part of the process, you know, that you soak it
and you wring it. So תוספות Tosafos says therefore there's another category
of סחיטה, sekhita, which is like squeezing fruit, when which is to
remove the food or the liquid, I should say the liquid, from
the sort of natural place in which it's contained. So if you
know you've got juice in the lemon and you squeeze the lemon,
that's a type of דש. dash. That's like when you thresh the
grain and you remove it from the husk, so you're removing the
liquid, you know, from its husk, from where it grows in the
lemon. Now of course this is funny because this is not its
natural location, it got absorbed into the cloth. And but nevertheless תוספות
Tosafos wants to say that this is it and it sounds like
he was still דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, and therefore what you're doing wrong is
that you're getting the wine out of the cloth. But תוספות Tosafos
says a problem, not just you don't want it, that's אינו מתכוין.
eino mitkavein. תוספות Tosafos, says but it's הולך לאיבוד. holekh le-ibud. And
הולך לאיבוד, holekh le-ibud, right? If it's hitting the ground and it's
not even being preserved, that's like it's מקלקל mekalkel and it's even
worse than מקלקל mekalkel or even better, meaning it's like you know
if you don't even have part of the מלאכה is that the
stuff gets caught and preserved, and הולך לאיבוד holekh le-ibud is like
you know it's at least מקלקל mekalkel if not that you're completely
פטור. patur So so why should this be a problem all together?
Right? A, it's not ליבון, libun, it's not it's not laundry, and
if it's about getting out wine, that would only be if you
were like capture the wine, you know, and not if you're if
it's הולך לאיבוד. holekh le-ibud. So that's what this big תוספות Tosafos.
tries to figure out, okay, which is why is it a problem
altogether altogether? Well it's not exactly clear what the answer is. The
question is more interesting than the answer. Okay. So but the other
interesting thing that emerges from this תוספות Tosafos is is that
before we get to the fact of מקלקל mekalkel. and הולך לאיבוד,
holekh le-ibud, he has another question, which is why is it אסור
asur, if it's an if it's an אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein, right,
and you're in the, if it's אינו מתכוין eino mitkavein and it's
a פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה. psik reisha delo nikha leih. That's
what it is. Like, you're not intending, it'll definitely happen, but you
have no interest in the result. Okay. Is that מותר לכתחילה muttar
lekhatchila or אסור לכתחילה? assur lekhatchila? And that's a major discussion in
the ערוך Arukh and in the ראשונים Rishonim and that's where תוספות,
tosfos the major one of the major locations where that discussion takes
place, right, is in this תוספות. tosfos, So again I will read
this to you just because this is a really important תוספות tosfos,
for הלכות שבת Shabbos because אינו מתכוין פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה,
eino mitkavein psik reisha delo nikha leih, I know that's like three
technical terms, but that happens all the time. That things happen that
you don't want them to happen, they're definitely going to happen, but
you don't care that they're happening, right? Brushing your hair and a
strand comes out, right? You know, opening your car door, let's say,
I don't know, you left something in your car and you want
to go retrieve it or whatever, right? But you know, opening your
refrigerator drawer, that's where, you know, and you left the light on
and there's total light in the room or whatever, you don't need
the light, so לא איכפת ליה. lo ichpas lei. לא ניחא ליה
lo nicha lei like so לא איכפת ליה lo ichpas lei is
it's there's no basically the ראשונים rishonim don't make a distinction, just
you're uninterested, not that you don't and don't want it.
Okay? So if you want to basically I'll just read you that
so this תוספות tosfos is huge, not only in size, important because
it conceptualizes two types of סחיטה sechita and because it addresses this
issue of פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה. psik reisha d'lo nicha lei.
So I'll just read you one line about that because that happens
all the time and it says like this, it says,
okay,
four lines down in the wide line. Does everybody see that?
It says והכא אמר רבינו תם דאיכא למימר דאסור משום מפרק. ve'hacha
amar Rabbeinu Tam d'ika l'meimar d'asur mishum mefarek.
You can't say it's prompt because of
מפרק mefarek like דש, dash, like squeezing fruit.
שמן שנסחט הולך לאיבוד. shemen shenischat holeich l'ibud. So that won't work
either why?
This oil is getting destroyed.
אף על גב דהוי פסיק רישא, af al gav de'havei psik reisha,
even though it's a פסיק רישא, psik reisha, this is worse than
a פסיק רישא. psik reisha I mean this is like better, you
know, it's even it's all getting lost and destroyed and it's מקלקל
mekalkel or even or even less than that.
וכן פירש בערוך דכל פסיק
רישא דלא ניחא ליה שרי.
v'chen peireish be'aruch
dechol
psik reisha d'lo nicha lei shari. Okay, any פסיק רישא דלא ניחא
ליה psik reisha d'lo nicha lei should be permissible. So even if
you don't introduce the idea of מקלקל mekalkel and הולך לאיבוד, holeich
l'ibud, this whole thing should be מותר mutar because it's a פסיק
רישא דלא ניחא ליה, psik reisha d'lo nicha lei, and פסיק רישא
דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha d'lo nicha lei should be מותר. mutar.
And then he goes through that whole discussion and then he says
that the ר''י Ri disagrees and the ר''י Ri says פסיק רישא
דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha d'lo nicha lei is אסור, asur. etc.
Okay, so just wanted to introduce you that this idea of מסוכרייא
דנזייתא mesuchraya d'nazeita is a big two words in הלכה. halacha. Okay,
so yes. Yes. Yes. Can I just ask you a question?
At the very beginning of that תוספות, tosfos. I just saw אומר
בסדר תנאים ואמוראים. omer b'Seder Tannaim ve'Amoraim.
Yeah, it's yeah, I
don't it's an early work of ראשונים rishonim that basically sort of,
you know, sort of like lists the different תנאים ואמוראים, Tannaim ve'Amoraim,
sort of like the way the ערוך Aruch is a dictionary but
through being a dictionary he deals with סוגיות sugyos in the גמרא,
Gemara and like right here he deals with a סוגיא. Sugya Yeah,
yeah.
And he and
so, you know, so it's a
so the ערוך Aruch is a dictionary but it also is written
in the end of the גאונים Geonim period and winds up interpreting
and therefore פוסק-ing poskening certain things in the גמרא. Gemara So סדר
תנאים ואמוראים Seder Tannaim ve'Amoraim is similar. I think it's some type
of a chronology identification of the various תנאים ואמוראים Tannaim ve'Amoraim and
as such quotes related סוגיות sugyos to them and also deals with
certain הלכות. Yes, but I don't remember the more specifics but I
do believe we do have it. Yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay, so back to this. So can רב Rav really say אינו
מתכוון eino miskavein is מותר? mutar? דאמר רב שימי בר חזקיה משמיה
דרב האי מסוכרייא דנזייתא אסור להדוקה ביומא טבא. de'amar Rav Shimi bar
Chizkiya mishmeih de'Rav hai mesuchraya d'nazeita asur l'haduka beyoma tava. You can't
tighten it. So obviously that's based on an idea that אינו מתכוון
is still going to be אסור. asur So the גמרא Gemara, says
בההוא אפילו רבי שמעון מודה. be'hahu afilu Rabi Shimon modei. No, רב
Rav could generally be of the position that אינו מתכוון is מותר,
mutar, but the case of the rag he would concede. Why is
it a problem? דאביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו. de'Abaye ve'Rava d'amri tarveihu. אביי
Abbaye and רבא Rava both say, and here we're introducing the idea,
מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות. modei Rabi Shimon b'psik reisha
v'lo yamut.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. agrees that if you can't say you're not
intending if you chop off the head of a chicken it's definitely
going to die. You can't say, so the classic example given is
do you want to chop off the head to use a little
chicken head as a ball to kick around for the kids? I'm
serious, that's what I think רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says or something
or רש''י Rashi says. Anyway, but nevertheless, oh, I didn't intend for
it to die. Like if it's definitely going to happen, you can't
say you didn't intend for it, or it's as if you intended
for it even though you're not interested. And this is the principle
of אינו מתכוון does not is not an exemption in the case
of פסיק רישא. psik reisha. And then the question becomes as I
was mentioning earlier in the תוספות, Tosafos what if though you are
you don't want that result? It's לא ניחא ליה lo nicha lei
or what if minimally you're you the result is of no interest
to you, of no value to you, לא איכפת ליה. lo ichpas
lei. So there, pretty much the ראשונים rishonim agree that you're לא
חייב, lo chayav, that you have not transgressed שבת. Shabbos According to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, that אינו מתכוון is מותר, mutar, פסיק רישא
psik reisha says it stops being מותר, mutar, but if it's לא
ניחא ליה lo nicha lei or לא איכפת ליה, lo ichpas lei,
at least you haven't biblically transgressed. And then there's the debate in
the ראשונים rishonim whether it's even מותר לכתחילה. mutar l'chatchila.
And that's what תוספות Tosafos said. He quotes the ערוך Aruch that
says it's מותר לכתחילה, mutar l'chatchila, other ראשונים rishonim say it's not
מותר לכתחילה. mutar l'chatchila. Big question in הלכה. halacha. Can you rely
on the ערוך Aruch and so on? Maybe you can rely on
the ערוך Aruch if you're dealing with an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabanan
or בשעת הדחק, beshas hadchak, but this is the issue that first
you get the allowance of אינו מתכוון, then you get the pull
back when it's פסיק רישא, psika reisha. then you get the allowance
again when it's לא ניחא lo nicha or לא איכפת ליה, lo
ichpas lei, at least to say that it's not אסור דאורייתא. asur
d'oreisa. Whether it's מותר דרבנן, mutar d'rabanan, that's the issue in תוספות.
Tosafos And that's why תוספות Tosafos is saying if you think it's
מותר דרבנן, mutar d'rabanan, then you're back to square one. So why
can't you squeeze the thing, right? Fine, it's a פסיק רישא דלא
ניחא ליה. psik reisha d'lo nicha lei. You're still back to the
question of why you're not allowed to do it. So that's what
that תוספות Tosafos deals with here.
Did it ever occur to you before but the whole idea of
פסיק רישא psika reisha is לא ניחא ליה? lo nicha lei? Just
because you want to use the chicken fat for oil?
Right. Well, maybe you want, maybe you wanted that chicken, maybe well
also want to eat chicken tonight or something, so, but you're right.
I mean some say that the actual, some אחרונים acharonim say, is
that what it is? Is that אינו מתכוין פסיק רישא? eino mischavein
psik reisha? Why isn't that a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha she'eina
tzricha l'gufa? You know, which gets to that whole question. Why is
a פסיק אינו מתכוין פסיק רישא psik eino mischavein psik reisha not
a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa? You're doing it,
you know what you're doing, you're not interested in that result, you're
interested in a different result. So some אחרונים acharonim say it is
the same and that's why it's and that's why it's it's אסור
asur to do פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha d'lo nicha
lei the same way it's אסור asur? to do a מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa. Okay, but yeah, some say to
answer your point that even if that case was a לא ניחא,
lo nicha, it's more used as like a metaphor. It's not said
that technically, you know, but some say give me a break. You
think you can say, oh, I wasn't intending because whatever whatever. All
right.
So we're just supposed to keep in mind through this whole discussion
that the תלמוד Talmud is really talking about the wedding night on
שבת Shabbat. and this is all about a woman?
Yes. Exactly. Well, you came a little late. If you had come
on time to class you would have so embarrassed.
All right. So anyway, moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. All right, so all right, so it's it's now half an
hour and we've read eight lines. So moving on. Okay, דאמר ליה
רב, d'amar lei Rav, okay fine. So how can רב Rav say
it's permissible? That suggests that how can רב Rav say it's אסור?
asur Oh sorry, one more time. How could how could רב Rav
say it's permissible? Doesn't רב Rav say you can't tighten the the
the rag, which basically suggests that it's you know that אינו מתכוין
eino mischavein is אסור asur.
and therefore and presumably the allowance of the previous case is based
on אינו מתכוין? eino mischavein? So the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, רב
Rav basically does say אינו מתכוין eino mischavein is מותר. mutar. Oh,
that's different because it's a פסיק רישא. psika reisha Why our case
is not a פסיק רישא we haven't gotten to yet, but we're
basically saying רב Rav could still in principle hold אינו מתכוין eino
mischavein is מותר, mutar, which is why he allows this case of
sex on שבת. Shabbat It should be pointed out, by the way,
that the whole issue of the tightening of the hole in the
barrel and the coming out of the wine or whatever seems very
graphically similar to what we're discussing about in terms of the woman
here.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. You late also? But
that's different than your point, Rabbi Dov. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, והאמר
רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב הלכה כרבי יהודה. v'ha'amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Ashi amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda. But one minute, we have
a statement of רבי חייא בר אשי Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi in
the name of רב Rav that explicitly that we rule like רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that אינו מתכוין eino mischavein is אסור. asur, רב
חנן בר אמי אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי שמעון. Rav Chanan bar Ami
amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. And רב חנן בר אמי Rav Chanan
bar Ami said in the name of שמואל Shmuel we rule like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon, So exactly the debate of רב Rav and
שמואל, Shmuel, there is a debate exactly also about whether אינו מתכוין
eino mischavein is permissible or forbidden. ורבי חייא בר אבין מתני בלא
גברי. v'Rabbi Chiya bar Avin masni belo gavrei. And רבי חייא בר
אבין Rabbi Chiya bar Avin teaches it without identify with, you know,
without like a tradition of names, just straight the just straight the
original position of רב. Rav. And he says yes, that רב אמר
הלכה כרבי יהודה ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי שמעון. Rav amar halacha k'Rabbi
Yehuda v'Shmuel amar halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. That רב Rav just straight רב
Rav says we rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and שמואל Shmuel
says we rule like רבי שמעון. So if רב Rav says we
rule like רבי יהודה that אינו מתכוין eino mischavein is אסור, asur.
how could רב Rav say you could have sex on שבת Shabbat
since most of the allowances yesterday were hinge were based on the
idea that you weren't intending and that it was an אינו מתכוין?
eino mischavein? So the גמרא Gemara says fine, but there were some
allowances that even some ways of making it permissible even without the
אינו מתכוין eino mischavein argument. And the גמרא Gemara says לעולם רב
כרבי יהודה סבירא ליה. l'olam Rav k'Rabbi Yehuda sevira lei. Fine, רב
Rav holds like רבי יהודה that אינו מתכוין eino mischavein is אסור.
asur והאי לישנא דאמר דמזקר פקיד. v'hai lishana d'amar dam mizkar pakid.
According to the idea that that the blood is like, you know,
is sort of like pooled, frankly, behind the hymen, but breaking of
the hymen doesn't exactly create a wound, so it's not a problem
of a wound, it's a problem of an opening.
So מקלקל הוא אצל פתח. mekalkel hu etzel pesach. We could say
it's not because you're אינו מתכוין, eino mischavein, it's מקלקל mekalkel. that
the husband although he you know is having sex with his wife,
at some level wants his wife to remain a virgin.
So you know, so it's considered a קלקול. kilkul. Like the woman
is no longer in her pristine state. So that's why, it's not
אינו מתכוין eino mischavein but מקלקל. mekalkel. והאי לישנא דאמר דם חיבורי
מיפטר. v'hai lishana d'amar dam chiburei miptar. And
according to the idea that there's also an idea of a wound
going on here, so מקלקל בחבורה הוא. mekalkel bachabura hu. Same idea,
that you say that it's considered to be a מקלקל mekalkel that
rather than saying it's a תיקון because he wants to see the
blood, it's a מקלקל because it's causing a wound. So basically, this
distills the point that there are two basic ways of making of
saying it was permissible: אינו מתכוין eino mischavein or מקלקל. You know,
and even and the גמרא Gemara says and even if אינו מתכוין
eino mischavein is not your position, you say אינו מתכוין eino mischavein
is אסור assur, or חייב, chayav the you could still be okay
because of מקלקל. Now, תוספות Tosafot by the way points out, to
continue this this you know not sort of whatever just abstracting this
in terms of the שבת Shabbat. point, which is that so what,
מקלקל isn't מותר לכתחילה. mutar l'chatchila. But he says okay. Fine, but
it's a מצוה mitzvah here, there's other extenuating circumstances, okay? But that's
another interesting question: just because things aren't חייב chayav, doesn't necessarily mean
it's מותר לכתחילה. mutar l'chatchila. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, so that's where we're up to, that רב Rav
basically says אינו מתכוון is אסור, assur. but he might hold that
it's מותר mutar to do, it's מותר mutar to have sex for
the first time on שבת, Shabbat although it's seeming to line up
that רב Rav is the one that would say it's אסור. מתיבי
רב חסדא: Masayvei Rav Chisda: רב חסדא Rav Chisda asked: תינוקת שלא
הגיע זמנה לראות, tinokes she-lo higia zemana liros, though here we're going
to go to actually having sex with an underage girl. If a
girl is less than twelve and she is, well, and not yet
her time to be having her period, this is a משנה Mishnah
in הלכות נדה. Hilchos Niddah.
And she is going ahead and she's married and she's having sex.
Okay, she's,
what can I tell
you, she's younger than that, she's not even of the age of
getting pregnant. And she has a wedding night. בית שמאי אומרים, Beis
Shammai omrim, now the point, the question that it's dealing with here
is
after the wedding night,
the woman is seeing blood. Is this דם נדה dam niddah or
not? Now, what occurs, the idea of the משנה Mishnah is that
דם בתולים, dam besulim, blood that comes through the rupture of the
hymen, is actually a way of exempting one from having to worry
about דם נדה, dam niddah, that even if we see some bleeding
for the next few days after the wedding night, we assume that
it's hymenal bleeding and the woman is not a נדה. niddah. The
irony happens that that's in the משנה, Mishnah, but in the time
of the גמרא Gemara and certainly later, it sort of starts in
the גמרא, Gemara it continues in the time of the גאונים Geonim
to come to its full sort of conclusion, that it reverses itself,
and we say that hymenal bleeding even when the woman is definitely
not menstruating, we will treat the hymenal blood as if it is
menstrual blood and the woman becomes a נדה niddah automatically. That is
not what you get in the משנה. Mishnah. In the משנה Mishnah
you get that even when a woman bleeds a few days after
the wedding night, we associate it with hymenal bleeding and we say
she's not a נדה. niddah. Now the question is: how many days
after? So there's a debate about, well, is she anyway of an
age of having her period? If she's really underage, I know it's
very disturbing to be describing these situations, if she's really underage, then
we're more likely to say even for a long time that this
is not menstrual bleeding because she's not even yet of the age
of having her period. If she's of the age of having her
period, then we will maybe limit the allowance to a shorter period
of time. So let's take a look. תינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות,
tinokes she-lo higia zemana liros, a young girl that it's not yet
the time for having her period, meaning her age of puberty, וניסת,
venissays, and she's married and has had sex on the wedding night.
בית שמאי אומרים נותנין לו ארבעה לילות, Beis Shammai omrim nosna lo
arba leilos, you give her the first four nights and any bleeding
then she's not a נדה, niddah, but after the first four nights
she is. ובית הלל אומרים עד שתחיה המכה, U-Veis Hillel omrim ad
she-tiyeh hamakah, no, it's indefinite until you're pretty confident that the wound
has healed, but you know it's not even limited by a specific
number of days. Now הגיע זמנה לראות, higia zemana liros, if however
it was a girl that has had her period or maybe not
had it but of the age of having her period, וניסת, venissays,
and she got married and it's wedding night. בית שמאי אומרים נותנין
לו לילה הראשון, Beis Shammai omrim nosna lo laila harishon,
only bleeding the first night is discounted. Afterwards we're concerned it's menstrual
blood. ובית הלל אומרים עד מוצאי שבת ארבעה לילות, U-Veis Hillel omrim
ad motzei Shabbos arba leilos,
until Saturday night four nights, because she got married on Wednesday, Wednesday
night, Thursday night, Friday night, Saturday night, okay, reflecting the idea that
virgins get married on Wednesday.
That's going to be the question. Okay, so here you have four
nights. So it suggests that she's having sex on שבת. Now the
point should be, well who cares that she's having sex on שבת,
she had sex on Wednesday night? The whole point was can you
have sex for the first time on שבת? But the point is
that we're assuming that the bleeding that's occurring is because of the
hymenal bleeding, so presumably we're assuming that it's occurring during the act
of sex and during the friction that's occurring
with what's left of the hymen during sex. And therefore even though
it's the third night that they're having sex, it's a similar scenario.
Having sex will lead to bleeding.
And therefore we think that this is therefore relevant for our discussion.
Now you could say, maybe it depends, is it a bleeding issue,
is it an opening issue, right, etc. But the גמרא Gemara assumes
even though it's not the first night, the גמרא Gemara assumes it's
relevant to the discussion. You see you're having sex on שבת on
Friday night and it's leading to bleeding and we're not concerned about
it. Okay, so that's the point. מאי לאו, mai lav, is it
not talking about דאילו בעל מצי בעל, de-ilu bo'al matzi bo'al, if
he hasn't had sex for the first time he's allowed to have
sex? Now again that sounds like he hasn't had sex at all
Wednesday night, which is then crazy. Then what do you mean by
four nights, the whole thing doesn't make sense. So תוספות Tosafot reframes
this as meaning that again, that the ביאה be'iah is somehow not
finished, like there's still sex is still going to entail bleeding. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אפילו בשבת? afilu be-Shabbos? And you're allowed to
do it even on שבת?
אמר רבא לא לבר משבת. Amar Rava: lo, levar mi-Shabbos. No, it
means four nights you have it until Saturday night, but assuming you're
not having sex on Friday night.
אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. והא עד מוצאי שבת ארבע לילות
קתני. veha ad motzei Shabbos arba leilos katani. It says, until Saturday
night, four nights, you're given, you know, so it's very clear every
single night is assumed that you're having sex and there's bleeding and
it's not a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רבא
כשבעל, ella amar Rava keshe-baal, you've already had sex. Now again, that's
the whole case. Whole case is you had sex and then there's
bleeding going on for four nights, but here presumably again to re-read
this through the way תוספות Tosafot re-phrases it, it means that you've
had sex and therefore you're not, you know, you're not really even
expecting bleeding to occur on the other nights. It's not like the
first night where it's like definitely going to entail bleeding, here it's
an unlikely occurrence. So the גמרא Gemara. says, וכי בעל מאי קא
משמע לן? veki ba'al mai ka mashma lan? So then what's the
חידוש? chiddush? Why say, I mean, the חידוש chiddush besides that for
four nights you don't have to worry that she's a נדה, niddah,
by saying four nights until מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbos underscores that they're
having sex on Friday night. What's the חידוש chiddush if there's no
real, you know, there's not much of a concern anymore that it'll
entail bleeding? So the גמרא Gemara says, קא משמע לן דשרי למיבעל
בשבת, ka mashma lan deshary lemiv'al beShabbos, כדשמואל, kedishmuel, that you can
have sex on שבת like שמואל, Shmuel, even if it's, you know,
even if it's like only the second or third time. Okay,
דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, פרצה דחוקה, pirtzah dechukah, so here's another image
like the barrel of wine or whatever, but this image is actually
used much more particularly in נדה, niddah, but in general throughout the
תלמוד Talmud about a woman and a woman's anatomy and having sex,
which is the image of a house and entering into a house.
Okay, so a narrow opening or a narrow break in the wall,
מותרת ליכנס בה בשבת, mutteres likannes bah beShabbos, if let's say there's
a,
this is the image. The image is you've got a stone wall
and you've got a little break in the wall and you can
squeeze yourself through that break in the wall, even though in the
process you lose, you know,
some stones, right, basically fall off. מותרת ליכנס בה בשבת ואף על
פי שמשיר צרורות, mutteres likannes bah beShabbos ve'af al pi shemeshir tzeroros,
even though it causes a few stones to fall off. So basically
so the point is, alright, so חידוש chiddush is that having sex
might entail some continued bleeding, but it's not the same type of
a definite thing, or if you want to go back to the
idea of an opening, it's not like the making of an opening
that we talked about for the first time. All right, but you
can't bring a proof from sex the third time to sex the
first time because obviously the situation here is different. But it is
allowed, and there is a חידוש chiddush that it's allowed because you
could have said, "Wait, wait, there still might be some bleeding." All
right, by the way, it's interesting because שמואל Shmuel is the one
who presumably says you can even have sex the first time on
שבת night. So what's the big חידוש chiddush that you could have
sex the third time on שבת night? Anyway, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. So although that seems to imply you're having sex on
שבת night, it's not such a big חידוש chiddush because you've already
had sex two nights ago. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. מתיב רב יוסף, masiv Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
asked, חתן פטור מקריאת
שמע לילה הראשון, chassan patur mikrias shema laylah harishon, עד מוצאי שבת,
ad motzei Shabbos, so a חתן chassan is exempt from saying שמע
Shema the first wedding night, because he's, his mind is distracted that
he's going to be having sex, and that would apply until Saturday
night, אם לא עשה מעשה, im lo asah ma'aseh, if he didn't
have sex. Again there's just idea of four nights, although again it
seems to be a different application,
because one is like he had sex and but for four
nights we sort of assume the bleeding continues, whereas here it's a
different point whereas we assume that for the first four nights, if
they didn't succeed to have sex, they're still working on having sex.
Whereas afterwards we sort of feel that there's a little bit of
a יאוש ye'ush that sets in. And by the way, that's like
a really, you know, it's a serious issue. You know some couples
it's a year later they haven't consummated their marriage, and, you know,
might be for various types of reasons, psychological, physiological, medical issues and
so on. I mean these things actually do happen. So here the
גמרא Gemara is saying like, you know, they're going to be trying
for the first four nights. Afterwards, a certain amount of a יאוש,
ye'ush, like giving up might set in, and what we do to
solve that situation is not addressed. But anyway, but for the first
four nights he's obviously focused on having sex and making, and, you
know, and therefore if he hasn't had it the first night, for
those first four nights, it's definitely what the plan of the evening
is, and therefore his mind is distracted and he's exempt from saying
קריאת שמע. krias shema. Now, the exemption in the פשט pshat of
the משנה, Mishnah, and the גמרא Gemara will get to this, probably
just has to do with an idea like, you know, that somebody
who is distracted, maybe specifically distracted by sexual thoughts, but even just
more generally is distracted, you know, is exempt from davening and from
שמע, Shema, specifically davening, but possibly even the even שמע, Shema, and
that certainly seems to be the פשט pshat of the משניות Mishnayos
and so on. The גמרא Gemara however in סוכה, Sukkah, and here
too, frames it as a type of an עוסק במצוה. osek bemitzvah.
That since you are thinking about—yeah, but that's but you're just influenced
by the גמרא Gemara in סוכה, Sukkah, that's not the פשט pshat
of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so anyway, okay, anyway, so but it's
a funny type of an עוסק במצוה osek bemitzvah because it's only
mental and you're not really preparing, you know, at that time, right.
But anyway, somehow that because you're mentally thinking about it, that makes
you considered involved in the מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so anyway, that's what
the גמרא Gemara assumes. Now, but what do you see? You see
that you're exempt for four nights including Friday night, which means that
on Friday... night you could you're planning on having sex that night
even though it would be the first time. So that's a good
evidence that you can have sex for the first time on Friday
night. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
עד מוצאי שבת לא עשה מעשה. מאי לאו דטריד דבעי למיבעל? Ad
Motzei Shabbat lo asa maaseh. Mai lav de-tarid de-ba'ei le-miv'al? Is it
not that he's distracted because he has to have sex and
this is the first time?
So you see you can have sex
on Friday night.
So אמרי ליה amrei leih for the first time. אמרי אביי, amrei
Abbaye, because this is רבא's Rava's proof. So רבא Rava said תירוץ
אביי teirutz Abbaye
לא דטריד דלא בעל. lo de-tarid de-lo ba'al. No, he's not having
sex on Friday night, but he still his mind is distracted because
he's like you know he he's upset about the fact that they
haven't succeeded for the last two nights. Okay and that's why his
mind can't focus on the שמע, Shema, he's just very upset and
distracted. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמרי, amrei, so it's not about
עוסק במצוה osek be-mitzvah because they're not having sex that night. So
now אמרי רבא, amrei Rava, so רבא Rava says back to him:
ומשום טירדא פטור? u-mishum tirda patur? Just because somebody is sort of
distracted they're exempt? אלא מעתה טבעה ספינתו בים, ela me-atah tava'at sefinato
ba-yam, if a guy's boat sank in the sea, right? If he
just had a big if the stock market you know had a
big drop and the person is so distracted, הכי נמי דפטור? hachi
nami de-patur? Would you say they're exempt? וכי תימא הכי נמי, ve-khi
teima hachi nami, and if you say yes they would be exempt
because why not, somebody can't focus they're exempt. והא אמר רבי אבא
בר זבדה אמר רב: ve-ha amar Rabbi Abba bar Zavda amar Rav:
Wait one minute, רבי אבא בר זבדה Rabbi Abba bar Zavda says
in the name of רב: Rav: אבל חייב בכל המצות האמורות בתורה,
avel chayav be-chol ha-mitzvot ha-amurot ba-Torah, an אבל avel is obligated in
all the מצות mitzvot as opposed to an אונן onen who's exempt,
and אבל avel is obligated in all the מצות, mitzvot, חוץ מן
התפילין, chutz min ha-tefillin, except that an אבל avel doesn't put on
תפילין tefillin for the first day. It doesn't say first day but
that's the הלכה. halakha. שנאמר בהם פאר, she-ne'emar ba-hem pe'er,
because תפילין tefillin are described as like glory and therefore it's not
appropriate for a חתן choson to be like glorifying himself of שבעה,
Shiva, yeah, for a חתן choson to be glorifying himself with you
know at this time of the greatest anguish. אלא, ela, yeah right
however long the ימים yamim this is. So anyway so the the
ah so the point is but he's חייב chayav in everything, presumably
he's חייב Chayav, in שמע. Shema. Isn't he distracted? Isn't he distracted
by thoughts about the about the person who passed away? And nevertheless
we say you're חייב, Chayav so you see simple distraction is not
enough. It has to be because you're it's a type of a
mental involvement that relates to doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Now רש"י Rashi
says I don't understand, isn't an אבל avel supposed to be mourning?
Isn't that a type of a isn't his distraction מצוה mitzvah related?
So there's a very important רש"י Rashi here, let's take a look.
רש"י Rashi says
he says like this
you know let's read two more lines and then I'll and then
I'll read the רש"י Rashi because רש"י Rashi is going on two
lines later in the גמרא. Gemara Okay so רבא Rava says you
can't say distraction is enough because then an אבל Ovel would also
be exempt from שמע, Shema, so it's specifically because he's in the
process of doing a מצוה. mitzvah. So you see that you can
have sex for the first time on שבת. So the גמרא Gemara
says: אלא אמר רבא תנאי היא. ela amar Rava Tannai hi. So
what do you do with the fact that it seems like we
have clearly a משנה mishna here that exempts the חתן choson on
Friday night saying that you're allowed to have sex on שבת for
the first time and we had a ברייתא braita before that said
you are not allowed to have sex on שבת for the first
time? So it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. אלא אמר רבא תנאי
היא. ela amar Rava Tannai hi. דתניא חד: אם לא עשה מעשה
בראשון פטור אף בשני, בשני פטור אף בשלישי. de-tanya chad: im lo
asa maaseh ba-rishon patur af ba-sheni, ba-sheni patur af ba-shelishi. We have
one ברייתא braita about שמע Shema that says that if he did
not have sex the first night he's exempt the second night and
if he didn't have the second night he's exempt the third night.
The third night is Friday night. So we have one ברייתא braita
that explicitly exempts the חתן choson on Friday. ותניא
אידך: ראשון ושני פטור, שלישי חייב. ve-tanya idach: rishon u-sheni patur, shelishi
chayav.
By the third night he has to say שמע. Shema. Presumably not
just because it's exemption only lasts for two nights but presumably because
the third night is Friday night and שבת. So there's a debate
of תנאים Tannaim how long a חתן choson whether a חתן choson
is פטור patur in שמע Shema on Friday night and says רבא
Rava this is a debate of whether you're allowed to have sex
for the first time on Friday night and therefore the ברייתא braita
that this whole thing sort of start well the whole thing didn't
start with but a ברייתא braita we quoted two days ago that
said you can't have sex for the first time on Friday night
because it makes a wound, this really is just in the end
of the day it's a debate of תנאים Tannaim and we see
that by this question of whether the חתן choson is פטור on
Friday night. Okay so that's what רבא Rava says. ואביי, ve-Abbaye, what
would אביי Abbaye answer back? אביי Abbaye wants to say it's not
based on having sex that night and being עוסק במצוה, osek be-mitzvah,
it's based on distraction. So if it's based on distraction why would
some why would one תנא Tanna say that you're חייב Chayav. on
Friday night? So didn't אביי Abaye say it's not based on being
involved in a מצוה mitzvah it's based on distraction? So you'd be
distracted even if you're not having sex you'd be distracted on Friday
night. So the גמרא Gemara says: ואביי, ve-Abbaye, so אביי Abaye would
say back:
התם נמי בטירדא פליגי. hasam nami be-tirda paligi. There also that's what
they're debating. The one maybe they both agree that you can't have
sex on Friday night. One says it doesn't matter, you're distracted because
of you know because you didn't succeed the last two nights and
therefore that's enough to exempt you from saying שמע Shema and the
other one says no. No, simple distraction doesn't exempt you from saying
שמע. Shema. The only thing that exempts you from saying שמע Shema
is you're thinking about doing the מצוה Mitzvah that you're about to
do. Okay, and therefore, so that's what the debate is, whether or
not simple distraction exempts you from saying שמע. Shema. So רבא Rava
looks at this debate about Friday night and says you have to
it's pointing to a debate of whether you can have sex for
the first time, whether you're in the process of doing a מצוה.
Mitzvah. אביי Abaye looks at the debate and he says everybody could
hold you're not allowed to have sex for the first time and
the debate is what exempts you from שמע, Shema, being in the
process of doing the מצוה Mitzvah of having sex or is it
what exempts you is just being distracted. Now, if it's possible that
just being distracted exempts you, right, רשי Rashi says, רשי Rashi, goes
back and asks the question, so if just being distracted exempts you,
what about רבא's Rava question about why the אבל Ovel? is חייב,
isn't he also distracted? So look at this רשי, Rashi חייב in
שמע. Shema. So רשי Rashi says אביי Abaye it's about ten lines
before the lines get wide, אמר לך הכא נמי בטירדה פליגי, Amar
lach hacha nami betirda pligi, and the one who exempts from קריאת
שמע, Kriyas Shema, the one who exempts from שמע, Shema, לאו משום
דשרי למיעל, Lav mishum deshurei lemeyal, it's not because he thinks you're
going to have sex that night, אלא קסבר מצטער צער של מצוה
פטור מקריאת שמע, Ela kasavar mista'er tza'ar shel mitzvah patur mikriyas shema,
so not any distraction, a distraction that's rooted in a מצוה. Mitzvah.
Why are you anguished Friday night even if you're not going to
be having sex? You're anguished because you're upset about the fact that
you haven't succeeded in doing the מצוה Mitzvah the last two nights.
So that's considered a מצוה Mitzvah related צער Tza'ar and that's like
a legitimate צער Tza'ar and because it's a legitimate צער Tza'ar you're
exempt. You can't say every little thing that distracts you exempts you,
do you have a legitimate excuse or not? So if it's a
מצוה Mitzvah related צער, Tza'ar, that's a legitimate צער Tza'ar and therefore
you're exempt. How's that different than the? So that tells you why
if your boat sinks, for example, you're still חייב. If you're distracted
about your boat sinking, your obligation in שמע Shema is learn to
bracket it and have the focus you need for שמע. Shema. But
if it's a legitimate anguish, it's מצוה Mitzvah related, then you are
allowed, then you're not forced to sort of bracket it. Okay, but
what about the אבל? Ovel. So now רשי Rashi says something very
interesting about the אבל. Ovel, He says ולא דמי לאבל דטריד טירדא
דרשות, Velo dami l'ovel detarid tirda d'reshus,
it's not similar to אבל, Ovel
that's not a מצוה Mitzvah related צער. Tza'ar. Why not? שאין צערו
מצוה, She'ein tza'aro mitzvah,
his anguish is not a מצוה Mitzvah אף על פי שאבילותו מצוה,
Af al pi she'aveiluso mitzvah, even though his אבילות Avelus is a
מצוה. Mitzvah. So very interesting, right? רשי Rashi says that nobody is
talking to, nobody is telling the אבל that you have to be
anguished. אבילות Avelus is showing signs of mourning but
not necessarily being anguished. Now that's interesting because does רשי Rashi mean
that you're not supposed to be feeling bad at all? You're just
supposed to know אבילות Avelus is just a way of showing respect
for the one who passed away, so it's a sort of an
expression more of I don't know respect than of sorrow or than
of anguish. Or is רשי Rashi trying to distinguish, it's funny because
you know Rav Soloveitchik, he has extensive תורה Torah relating to אבילות
Avelus and he emphasizes that all of the external expressions are really
a ways of giving a קיום Kiyum of what's going on internally,
the internal experience of mourning. So maybe רשי Rashi isn't saying you're
not supposed to have an internal experience, maybe he's trying to distinguish
between an experience of mourning and an experience of suffering.
But even if you were to make that distinction, it's like okay
but even the experience of mourning even if it's not suffering that's
also distracting you know that also so it's very hard like why
is this less a type of a
legitimate distraction than the distract or a legitimate צער Tza'ar than the
צער Tza'ar of the guy who's upset that he didn't have sex
the last two nights? Okay, so it's a very strange גמרא Gemara
which is why the גמרא Gemara would rather frame it as עוסק
במצוה Osek bemitzvah than distraction because if you frame it as distraction
you have to be saying why is this the only distraction that
gets you off the hook and not other types of distractions.
Yes that's what I'm saying because as far as I understood doesn't
the גמרא Gemara also look Friday night is a general מצוה Mitzvah
for married couples? Yes that's עונה Onah so then you can be
exempt for קריאת שמע Kriyas Shema also because you're עוסק במצוה. Osek
bemitzvah.
Right, so no you're right. So the basic answer would be so
it's a good question why does the גמרא Gemara consider the first
night of sex to be a מצוה? Mitzvah? So I mean there's
a מצוה Mitzvah in general for husband and wife to be having
sex. So one answer could be so there's a
שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet on כתובות that says no, the reason the
גמרא Gemara calls the first time husband and wife are having sex
is an important point thank you for stopping on this, בעילת מצוה,
Beilas mitzvah, it means even the very first time is a מצוה
Mitzvah because remember the גמרא Gemara believes that a woman could not
become pregnant the first time she had sex when if she was
a virgin because so maybe the hymen they thought would prevent her
from becoming pregnant. So the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says every time
husband and wife have sex it's a מצוה Mitzvah when the גמרא
Gemara says the first time is a מצוה Mitzvah means even the
first time is a מצוה Mitzvah even though there's not the possibility
of becoming pregnant. Generally it's assumed that the גמרא Gemara is saying
that there's a special מצוה Mitzvah the first night. By the way,
what needs to be underscored is it does not mean the first
night after the wedding, it means the first time they're having sex,
right there very often are couples that feel like even if they're
not ready or whatever, especially if they have Haven't been being, if
they've been keeping הלכה Halacha and haven't been sexually active or, you
know, even had any sexual type of touch or anything, you know,
and now all of a sudden they're supposed to go straight into
having intercourse. So some people feel like you have to do it
the wedding night, it's a מצוה Mitzvah whatever. No. Even if you
say that there's a special מצוה, Mitzvah, it means the first time.
It doesn't mean it's a special מצוה Mitzvah to take place the
night of the wedding. And that's a very pervasive misconception which is
very harmful also misconception.
I've also wondered about that.
Yeah. So the פוסקים Poskim are clear about that except the common
perception is not that way. So that's very important to underscore. Let
me finish my point. That's very important number one to underscore that,
that even if it's specifically the מצוה Mitzvah the first time, it
doesn't mean that it has to be the night of the wedding.
So, why is the first time called a ביאת מצוה? Biat Mitzvah?
Either it means even the first time or it means no, there's
a special מצוה, Mitzvah, but the special מצוה Mitzvah is like the
גמרא Gemara said before about this whole idea of פתח Petach and
so on, that you know now the woman is becoming like
a, you know, physically mature not, you know, whatever, at a stage
where she's now ready to have like it sort of in her
very body signifies, you know, that she's going to be having a
sexual life with her husband and that's seen to be like that,
you know, that sort of initiating of that and that effecting of
that change is some it's seen to be like some special מצוה.
Mitzvah. Okay? But so that's why there might be a heightened idea
of מצוה Mitzvah on on that first time, but that's not דוקא
Davka the wedding night. I actually sort of reframed something because again
maybe I was trying to be a little less objectifying. The גמרא
Gemara the thing what תוספות Tosfos quotes. תוספות Tosfos quotes the גמרא
Gemara that says, אין האשה כורתת ברית אלא למי שעשאה כלי. Ain
Ha-Isha Koreset Brit Ela Lemi She'asa Keli. That the woman only makes
a covenant like has like this, you know, sense of deep emotional
like you know attachment permanent emotional attachment except to the man who
made her into a vessel. Okay, which gets into the whole גמרא
Gemara about making an opening and so on. So, I tried to
reframe that a little bit but I do want to be honest
that's what תוספות quotes why it might be a special מצוה Mitzvah
the first time. Not דוקא Davka the wedding night but the first
time. Anyway, so, but your question, why couldn't you always be exempt
because every time is a מצוה? Mitzvah? Even if you say the
first night is a special מצוה, Mitzvah, isn't every time a מצוה?
Mitzvah? And the answer might be, yeah, every time is a מצוה,
Mitzvah, but after the first time you're not distracted. Right? The whole
point here is that it's the first time you're doing it, so
it's a distraction and it's an acknowledged distraction, whereas afterwards if you're
still distracted after the first time, learn how to deal with it
and focus on saying the שמע. Shema.
Didn't we also have other things from the rabbis that like you
know they went on a journey for a couple days they still
didn't דאוון Daven I remember we spoke— Yeah,
so that's exactly why the argument of distraction is a pretty good
argument, but the גמרא— Gemara But you're saying—
I understand, I understand.
So that's the גמרא's Gemara why that pushes the גמרא Gemara. to
talk about it more in terms of a מצוה Mitzvah but yes
the simple sense is that this is probably much more rooted in
the issues of distraction. So where are we? Well, where we are
is we've introduced this idea of the חתן Chatan exempt the first
four nights including Friday night. This seems to point to the idea
that they that you can have sex for the first time on
Friday night, but רבא Rava says well maybe it's a debate of
תנאים Tannaim because there's a debate of whether you're exempt on Friday
night, and אביי Abaye says maybe everybody holds that you're not having
sex on Friday night but the issue is whether the distraction exempts
you even if you're not in the process of doing a מצוה.
Mitzvah. Okay, so can you learn from the story here about the
חתן Chatan whether or not you're allowed to have sex on Friday
night? Again, that's open.
So let's take a look now at how the גמרא Gemara now
sort of takes this to the next stage and it says the
following: הני תנאי כהני תנאי. Hani Tannai Ke-Hani Tannai.
These תנאים Tannaim that seem to bottom line is it seems like
there's a debate of תנאים Tannaim whether you can have sex for
the first time on Friday night so by the case of the
חתן Chatan and שמע, Shema, this maps onto the following two תנאים
Tannaim which are what תנאים? Tannaim? דתניא, De-Tanya, הקונה את הבתולה לא
יבא בתחלה בשבת
וחכמים מתירין. Ha-Koneh et Ha-Betulah Lo Yavo Betchilah Be-Shabbat Ve-Chachamim Matirin. So
finally we said explicitly that it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
If you marry a virgin,
you can't have sex for the first time on שבת and the
חכמים Chachamim say you can. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מאן
חכמים, Man Chachamim, and who are the חכמים? Chachamim? אמר רבא רבי
שמעון היא, Amar Rava Rabbi Shimon Hi, it's רבי שמעון, דאמר דבר
שאינו מתכוין מותר, De-Amar Davar She-Eino Mitkaven Mutar, because we see that
so much rooted in this issue of אינו מתכוין. Eino Mitkaven. By
the way, this is probably the original סוגיא. Sugya. The original סוגיא
was probably this one line. We have a ברייתא Baraita that's a
debate, it's identified with רבי שמעון, and then after that we developed
a whole like logic tree yesterday
of all the theoretical different ways you could come to this conclusion,
right that gets redacted and then— exactly. But this is probably the
original סוגיא. אמר ליה אביי, Amar Lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye. said,
ומודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות. Ve-Modeh Rabbi Shimon Pesik Reisha
Ve-Lo Yamut. And we know אביי and רבא Rava both are of
this opinion. If it'll definitely happen, so if it'll definitely happen it
should still be a problem and won't this still definitely happen? So
why is אינו מתכוין Eino Mitkaven okay? So the גמרא says אמר
ליה, Amar Lei,
so רבא Rava said back, לא כאלו בבליים Lo Ka-Elu Bavlayim שאין
בקיאין בהטיה. She-Ein Beki'in Be-Hataya. Not like those Babylonians, probably meant non-Jews,
that aren't or whatever because he's a Babylonian too, that don't know
how to do an inclining. אלא יש בקיאין בהטיה, Ela Yesh Beki'in
Be-Hataya, there are those that know how to incline. meaning it's possible
to have sex and to sort of to penetrate in a more
horizontal way or whatever sideways way that doesn't rupture the hymen. So
it's not a פסיק רישא. It's possible. They could have sex for
first time without rupturing the hymen. So the גמרא says אם כן
im kein let me just read it אם כן im kein טרוד
למה. tarud lamah.
So if people are so good at avoiding rupturing the hymen why
how can he be so distracted the חתן? choson? The חתן choson
is distracted because he's not succeeding which probably means he's not so
adept. You know if people if we're assuming that they're adept and
how are they exactly adept if they haven't had any sexual experience
beforehand? So anyway so how could you both have somebody who is
adept and therefore it's not a פסיק רישא but also the same
type of a person who's distracted about having sex for the first
time? So the גמרא says okay there you go. So the גמרא
says it doesn't explain why it's why he's distracted. So if he's
good at doing it if if he theoretically if he'll be good
at doing it why why is he so distracted? So the גמרא
says טרוד למה לשאינו בקי. tarud lamah l'she'eino baki. So the one
who's not an expert. Of course it doesn't really fit because if
it's the one who's not an expert is the one who's exempt
then why is he allowed to be having sex on Friday night?
Like it doesn't you need to be the same person who it's
not going to be a פסיק רישא for who's also we're allowing
to have sex who's distracted. So תוספות tries to sort of work
it all out but it's very complicated. Anyway so the גמרא says
יאמרו בקי מותר שאינו בקי אסור? yomru baki mutar she'eino baki assur?
Oh what are they going to say? That if you're a בקי
baki and again how exactly you're getting to be a בקי baki
if it's the first time I don't know but if you're a
בקי baki you can have sex on Friday night. If you're not
a בקי baki that if you don't know how to do how
to be so so precise when you're having sex you're not allowed
to have sex on Friday night. So the גמרא says רוב בקיאין
הן. rov baki'in hen. Most people know. So really? Most people know
how to do this? And again how do most people learn how
to do this? Most men on their wedding night if they're supposed
to not have had any sexual experience. And who cares anyway about
most men? If this one man says I don't know how to
do it are we going to tell him oh then you can't
I don't know how to to prevent the breaking of the hymen
I don't know how to have sex I don't know how to
prevent the breaking of the hymen oh well then you can't have
sex Friday night. Is that what we're going to say? Who cares
about the רוב? rov? It should be about this individual person. So
I really don't even begin to understand this גמרא I just gotta
tell you. Okay I mean תוספות tries to figure it out but
I really don't understand it. Okay let's just read one more line.
אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנן לאביי. Amar leih Rava bar Rav
Chanan l'Abaye. So רבא בר רב חנן Rava bar Rav Chanan said
to אביי. אלא מעתה Ela mei'ata if people can have are can
have sex men can have sex without rupturing the
hymen אלא מעתה ela mei'ata ורוב בקיאין ve'rov baki'in שושבינין למה מפה
למה? shushbinin lamah mapah lamah? Why again you know you see this
on some like like movies about like what happened like you know
a few hundred years ago but this happened in times of the
גמרא. They would have people waiting outside the door to check the
sheets. I mean you sort of see it in the גמרא פרשו
השמלה לפני זקני העיר parsu hasimlah lifnei ziknei ha'ir the תורה Torah
ופרשו השמלה לפני זקני העיר u'parsu hasimlah lifnei ziknei ha'ir you check
the sheets to see the hymenal blood to prove that she's a
virgin. And the גמרא and you want to make sure that there
nobody is is cheating like you know smuggling in some blood or
whatever. So what you would do is you would have a pre-checked
sheet a מפה mapah and you'd have שושבינין shushbinin you'd have the
groomsmen like waiting outside the door and all of this we're going
to see this later is to prove that she actually you know
is or isn't a virgin. So the point is so the point
is well one minute though. If you can have sex without it
rupturing the hymen what type of a proof is this? Maybe she
is a virgin. Why are you bothering with the sheet and with
the groomsmen? So אמר ליה amar leih התם שמא יראה ויאבד ויאבד
hasam shema yireh ve'yoveid ve'ye'aveid
right there maybe maybe no there the problem is is that we
don't want that actually there is evidence and the evidence is lost.
So you want the groomsmen to come in right afterwards and to
make sure that the if there's evidence that it's found. Okay but
רש"י says okay but still you're going to claim she's not a
virgin when she is because of this. He says no no then
she'll say look you haven't you know I'm still a virgin let's
do it again and you'll see right because it just because it
didn't rupture the hymen the first time. So the bigger concern is
not that it won't you know that that the hymen won't have
ruptured but that it will have and the evidence will be lost.
And that's why you make sure you do all of this. Okay
so we will end with this for today.